<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>sulami's blog</title><link>https://sulami.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://sulami.github.io/feed/games.rss.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2014 23:55:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><item><title>Playing in space on Linux</title><link>https://sulami.github.io/playing-in-space-on-linux.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;While I have been working day and night lately on my (sort of) new
project, peerwire.org (which currently links to this blog, but will soon
go live), I have now reached the beta phase which will mostly be
intensive testing and trying to break the site, as well as some minor
technical fixes. But this aside, I now have some spare time while I wait
for some other stuff to happen, so I decided to play a game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have not played a game for quite some time, if you do not count
playing for less than 10 minutes, I probably have not played a game this
year. As I do not have a Windows partition anymore (which I am quite
proud of, Linux and to some degree BSD achieve everything I need), I
only have my collection of right now 66 Steam games for Linux (out of
200 I own). Today I had another look at Kinetic Void, a kickstarted game
I picked up for 2.50€ when it hit Greenlight some time ago. It is still
in early alpha and not even close to feature-complete, but it is already
quite gorgeous if you like spaceships.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Screenshot from 2014-04-11 23:50:47" src="/images/Screenshot-from-2014-04-11-235047-1024x576.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are some other really cool games for Linux on Steam and most of
them are also rather cheap, but you can sink hundreds of hours into
some.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://store.steampowered.com/app/220200/" title="Steam"&gt;Kerbal Space Program&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More spaceships, more simulation. Pretty intensive on the hardware, my
high-end Intel CPU without dedicated GPU can barely run in, but it
works. Check the &lt;a href="http://wiki.kerbalspaceprogram.com/wiki/Main_Page" title="KSP Wiki"&gt;Wiki&lt;/a&gt; for infos and how to learn the game, also
YouTube has some great tutorials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://store.steampowered.com/sub/12985/" title="Steam"&gt;X3: Reunion, X3: Terran Conflict, X3: Albion Prelude&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been playing the X-games since the first one, although I do not
own the latest one yet, as it seems to be the worst yet and I do not
really game anymore. 4X spaceship sandboxes with some story, huge
universe, top-notch graphics, really complicated and hard to get into.
But immense fun. If you start, get TC or AB, Reunion does lack some
important convenience features. The best resource I know of is
&lt;a href="http://www.seizewell.de/" title="Seizewell"&gt;Seizewell&lt;/a&gt;, which is German, as X comes from Germany and is played
there the most.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://store.steampowered.com/app/212680/" title="Steam"&gt;FTL: Faster Than Light&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a spaceship rogue-like, which means you select a ship, and start
on a journey to do whatever, until you either die or complete the story.
Than you start again. There are some well-made mods around to extend the
fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://store.steampowered.com/app/107200/" title="Steam"&gt;Space Pirates and Zombies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An interesting space arcade action adventure game which really leads to
addiction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are some games for Linux that are more or less space-related I
have not tested yet, maybe someone can give me a tip on one of those:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://store.steampowered.com/app/246090/" title="Steam"&gt;Spacebase DF-9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://store.steampowered.com/app/255500/" title="Steam"&gt;Entropy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://store.steampowered.com/app/257930/" title="Steam"&gt;Race to Mars&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://store.steampowered.com/app/212070/" title="Steam"&gt;Star Conflict&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://store.steampowered.com/app/233250/" title="Steam"&gt;Planetary Annihilation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I hear, Star Citizen will also be on Linux, which will hopefully be a
great experience, maybe even a reason for me to install a GPU again. I
am also still waiting for Planetside 2 to come to Linux, which is really
fun with a bunch of friends (but also runs like shit)&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">sulami</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2014 23:55:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:https://sulami.github.io,2014-04-11:playing-in-space-on-linux.html</guid><category>games</category><category>steam</category><category>linux</category></item><item><title>Get the freaking Humble Bundle!</title><link>https://sulami.github.io/get-the-freaking-humble-bundle.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;If you are a Linux gamer like me (although I barely play games anymore
as I don't have the free-time I used to have anymore), get the &lt;a href="http://humblebundle.com" title="Humble Bundle"&gt;Humble
Bundle&lt;/a&gt;. For some dollars you get 6 great games, 5 with native
Linux-support, one that will get a native Linux version later this year
for free, all the soundtracks as mp3s and flacs, and there is hidden
stuff which will be unlocked later on. What are you waiting for?&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">sulami</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2014 15:49:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>tag:https://sulami.github.io,2014-02-19:get-the-freaking-humble-bundle.html</guid><category>gaming</category></item></channel></rss>